Jerome Kern Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Jerome Kern Collection1905-1945
ML31.K4
Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945
circa 7,450 items 102 boxes 45 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists primarily of Kern's show music, some holograph sketches; most are manuscript full and vocal scores of Kern's orchestrators and arrangers, especially Frank Saddler and Robert Russell Bennett. Film and other music also is represented, as well as a small amount of correspondence.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bennett, Robert Russell, 1894-1981.; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945--Correspondence.; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945.; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945.; Kern, Jerome, 1885-1945. Selections.; Saddler, Frank.
Subjects
Composers--United States--Correspondence.; Musical sketches.; Musicals--Scores.; Musicals--Vocal scores with piano.
Titles
Kern collection, 1905-1945
Administrative Information
Provenance
The bulk of the material, discovered in a Warner Bros. warehouse in Secaucus, N.J., in 1982, was acquired from Betty Kern-Miller (the composer's daughter) between 1986 and 1990. Additional items were donated by Rodgers & Hammerstein, T.B. Harms, and John McGlinn, or purchased.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Jerome Kern Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. The following paragraphs provide instructions for reproducing items in the Jerome Kern Collection:
1. Reproduction for Research and Scholarship. Starting on January 1, 2010, all materials in the Collection may be reproduced by Library patrons for the purposes of research and scholarship without the permission of the Estate and/or Trust.
2. Reproduction for Other Uses. Starting on January 1, 2010, the following will apply with regard to reproduction for uses other than research and scholarship of materials in the Collection:
a) In the United States. For use in the United States, all of the Collection materials published prior to 1923 may be reproduced by Library patrons without the permission of the Estate and/or Trust. Any further uses of the materials are governed by U.S. copyright law
b) In Foreign Territories. Any use of materials outside the United States is governed by the applicable copyright law of the territory in which such use occurs.
3. Contact for Permissions. Persons wishing to reproduce materials in the Collection for uses other than those permitted herein will be advised to contact the Estate of Betty Kern Miller and the Betty Kern Miller Literary Trust, c/o R. Andrew Boose, Davis Wright Tremaine, 1633 Broadway, New York, New York 10019, andrewboose@dwt.com
Biographical Note
Date Event
1885, Jan. 27 Jerome David Kern is born in New York City to Henry Kern and Fanny Kakeles
1902 Kern studies harmony, theory and the piano at the New York College of Music
1903 Kern studies music theory and composition in Heidelberg, Germany
1904 Kern works as a song-plugger (notably for T. B. Harms) and as a rehearsal pianist in Broadway theatres. Kern begins interpolating songs into musicals
1905 The Earl and the Girl opens in New York; "How'd You Like to Spoon with Me?" is interpolated into the score
1906 Kern works in London, interpolating songs into musical shows
1910, Oct. 25 Kern marries Eva Leale in England
1912, Nov. 13 The Red Petticoat opens in New York
1913, Oct. 30 Oh, I Say! opens in New York
1914 The Girl from Utah opens in New York; "They Didn't Believe Me" is interpolated into the score
1915, Jan. 15 Ninety in the Shade opens in New York
1915, April 20 Nobody Home opens in New York
1915, Dec. 23 Very Good Eddie opens in New York
1917, Jan. 11 Have a Heart opens in New York
1917, Jan. 15 Love o' Mike opens in New York
1917, Feb. 20 Oh, Boy! opens in New York
1917, Aug. 28 Leave It to Jane opens in New York
1918, Feb. 1 Oh, Lady! Lady!! opens in New York
1918, March 11 Toot-Toot! opens in New York
1918, April 29 Head Over Heels opens in New York
1918, May 22 Rock-a-Bye Baby opens in New York
1918, Dec. 16 Kern's daughter Elizabeth (Betty) Jane Kern is born
1919, May 5 She's a Good Fellow opens in New York
1920, Feb. 2 Night Boat opens in New York
1920, Dec. 21 Sally opens in New York
1921, Nov. 1 Good Morning Dearie opens in New York
1922, Sept. 19 The Cabaret Girl opens in London
1922, Nov. 28 The Bunch and Judy opens in New York
1923, Sept. 5 The Beauty Prize opens in London
1923, Nov. 6 Stepping Stones opens in New York
1924, April 8 Sitting Pretty opens in New York
1924, Sept. 23 Dear Sir opens in New York
1925, Sept. 22 Sunny opens in New York
1925, Oct. 26 The City Chap opens in New York
1926, Oct. 12 Criss Cross opens in New York
1927, March 22 Lucky opens in New York
1927, April 27 Blue Eyes opens in London
1927, Dec. 27 Show Boat opens in New York
1929 Sally (film) opens
1929 Show Boat (film) opens
1929, Sept. 2 Sweet Adeline opens in New York
1930 Sunny (film) opens
1931 Men of the Sky (film) opens
1931, Oct. 15 The Cat and the Fiddle opens in New York
1932, Nov. 8 Music in the Air opens in New York
1933 The Cat and the Fiddle (film) opens
1933, Nov. 18 Roberta opens in New York
1934, April 9 Three Sisters opens in London
1934 Music in the Air (film) opens
1935 I Dream Too Much (film) opens
1935 Roberta (film) opens
1935 Sweet Adeline (film) opens
1936 Show Boat (2nd film) opens
1936 Swing Time (film) opens
1937 High, Wide and Handsome (film) opens
1937 When You're in Love (film) opens
1938 The Joy of Living (film) opens
1938 Gentlemen Unafraid opens in St. Louis
1939, Nov. 17 Very Warm for May opens in New York
1940 One Night in the Tropics (film) opens
1941 Lady Be Good (film) opens, "The Last Time I Saw Paris" is interpolated into the score
1941 Sunny (2nd film) opens
1942 You Were Never Lovelier (film) opens
1944 Can't Help Singing (film) opens
1944 Cover Girl (film) opens
1945, Nov. 11 Kern dies in New York
1946 Centennial Summer (film) opens
Scope and Content Note
The Jerome Kern Collection consists primarily of Show Music (Series I). The music in the collection includes a number of holograph sketches and scores, but the majority of the music is not in Kern's hand; however, much of this music does contain annotations by Kern.
Many of the music manuscripts are by Kern's orchestrators and arrangers. The full scores of Frank Saddler and Robert Russell Bennett are particularly well represented. Over fifty of Kern's shows are represented in the collection, from the 1906 shows The Spring Chicken and Fluffy Ruffles, to Kern's last Broadway musical Very Warm for May from 1939.
In a 1940 letter to Harold Spivacke, then Chief of the Music Division, Jerome Kern wrote of his plan to give a manuscript to the Library: "I shall be glad to send [the manuscript] on with no small amount of pride, not in the composition, but in its destination." The Library of Congress, in turn, is proud to count the Jerome Kern Collection among its holdings. The Library is particularly fortunate in the quantities of full scores and parts we have for what are considered Kern's most significant scores: The Cat and the Fiddle, Music in the Air, Roberta, Sally, Show Boat, Sitting Pretty, Sunny, Sweet Adeline, Very Good Eddie and Very Warm For May.
In addition, the Miscellaneous Music (Series II) is mostly comprised of copies of late songs by Kern. Many of these were songs that were cut from films, or written for unproduced projects. In some cases, lyrics were added to previously unused works after Kern's death. Apparently, most of this material came from the files of T. B. Harms, Inc. (Kern's publisher) and some appear to have been transcribed from recordings made by Kern. There are indications that these materials had been compiled to create a Jerome Kern revue in the 60's that Cheryl Crawford had considered producing.
All annotations in Kern's hand are not listed in this document. For instance, among the unacknowledged holographic annotations are a number of music manuscripts in the hand of a copyist or arranger, but on which Kern wrote the title. In cases where notes by Kern were particularly interesting or revealing, they have been transcribed as notes in this Guide. It may be helpful to know that Kern used the term "melos" to refer to underscoring, and the term "burthen" to refer to a chorus or refrain.
Songs preceded by an asterisk "*" were not composed by Kern. When a song title is followed by "#" and a number or combination of numbers and letters, that designation appears on all or most of the items listed below that title, indicating its position in the running order of the stage work. These numbers are supplied here for purposes of differentiating multiple versions of the same song title, or to indicate songs that at least appear to have made it into the rehearsal process for a production of the show. These numbers may also be helpful in differentiating between music used in various productions of the same show. When a portion of a song title is crossed through on the music, it is also crossed through in the Guide.
A number of people contributed to the organization, identification, and processing of this collection. Prior to the collection's coming to the Library, an enormous amount of work was done by Robert Kimball, John McGlinn and Alfred Simon. Mssrs. Kimball and McGlinn have been generous in their subsequent assistance, as has Gerald Bordman, whose book Jerome Kern: His Life and Music (Oxford University Press, 1980), has also been a significant resource. Finally, I would like to express my gratitude to my co-worker, Albert Tucker, whose eagle-eyed attention to detail proved invaluable in the processing of this collection.
Mark Eden Horowitz, 1994
Organization of the Jerome Kern Collection
The Jerome Kern Collection is organized in 3 series:
Show Music
Miscellaneous Music
Correspondence
http://lccn.loc.gov/95702650
Container List
- Show Music (Box 1-95, Box 103-116)
  The Jerome Kern Collection consists primarily of Show Music (Series I). The music in the collection includes a number of holograph sketches and scores, but the majority of the music is not in Kern's hand; however, much of this music does contain annotations by Kern. Many of the music manuscripts are by Kern's orchestrators and arrangers. The full scores of Frank Saddler and Robert Russell Bennett are particularly well represented. Over fifty of Kern's shows are represented in the collection, from the 1906 shows The Spring Chicken and Fluffy Ruffles, to Kern's last Broadway musical Very Warm for May from 1939. The Library is particularly fortunate in the quantities of full scores and parts we have for what are considered Kern's most significant scores: The Cat and the Fiddle, Music in the Air, Roberta, Sally, Show Boat, Sitting Pretty, Sunny, Sweet Adeline, Very Good Eddie and Very Warm For May.
  Note: there are 2 full sets of parts for Roberta (1933), 1 regular size (without any piano parts) and 1 oversize (which contains parts for piano's I & II.) The oversize parts appear to be somewhat more recent; when 2 numbers appear on these parts the greater number is usually the original and is frequently crossed out and replaced with the lower number. In addition, there are some additional parts, at least some of these appear to have been for the film and are written on RKO paper; it is not clear what productions contained "Orientale" and "Pitkin".
  Note: a number of Leave it to Jane (1917) pieces include the show title Widow, which presumably comes from the original play on which Leave It to Jane was based -- The College Widow.
  The show music in the Kern collection has first been organized alphabetically by show title, and within each show, alphabetically by song title. The music has further been physically organized by type -- full scores, piano-vocal scores, and parts. When there is more than a box or two of music for an individual show, these various types of material have been boxed separately. In this way, researchers may request boxes of just full scores, or just piano-vocal scores, or just parts. In many cases, the full scores had to be housed separately because of their large size.
  - Manuscripts (Box 1-94, Box 103-116)
    - The Arrow (1905) poem by Longfellow
      - [The arrow], Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink, no lyric; [4] p.; Ms. lyric sheet in pencil; [1] p.; On t.p.: "Jerome D. Kern./Some where in England/Some time in 1905" (Box-folder 1/1)
      - The arrow: [in F], Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; [4] p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - The arrow: [in G], Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; [4] p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - The arrow: [in F], Ms. piano-vocal score in pencil; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/2)
    - The Beauty Prize (1923) lyrics by P.G. Wodehouse
      - Non stop dancing: no. 14, Ms. (Stephen O. Jones) piano-vocal score in ink, some pencil annotations in Kern's hand, no lyric; 4 p. (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Blue Eyes (1928) lyrics by Graham John
      - Girls of London [and unidentified titles], Holograph sketches in ink and pencil; [2] p. (Box-folder 1/4)
      - His Majesty's dragoons, Holograph sketches in ink and pencil; [4] p.; On t.p.: "(N.B. 'Show boat' on back.)" (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Scena, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink, no lyric; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/6)
    - The Bunch and Judy (1922) lyrics by Anne Caldwell
      - Clansmen: march past, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink, annotations in Kern's hand; 15 p.; On t.p.: "'Blue Eyes' go to p. 6"; Note: used in Toot-Toot! and Stolen Dreams (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Fling, Ms. sketch in pencil on back of above; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Ev'ry day, Ms. orchestra sketch in pencil; [2] p.; Uniform title: Every day in every way (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Ev'ry day: Fred & Adele Astaire, Holograph sketch in pencil; [2] p.; Uniform title: Every day in every way (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Have you forgotten me? blues: Why don't you write to me blues?, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 9 p.; Typed lyric sheet laid in; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Home, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Hot dog, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 5 p.; Typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Hot dog: Dance duet, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 6 p. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - The pale Venetian moon, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 5 p. (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Can't Help Singing
      - [Various titles] see: Series II -- Miscellaneous Music
    - Caroline
      - [Various titles] see: Series II -- Miscellaneous Music
    - The Cat and the Fiddle (1931) lyrics by Otto Harbach
      - Act I scene 2, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 48 p. (Box-folder 1/13)
      - Act I scene 2: #2, Parts (Box-folder 4/11)
      - Act I scene IV: love parade, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 50 p. (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Act I scene IV: love parade: #3, Parts; Includes: "#3b" (Box-folder 4/12)
      - Act II scenes I and II, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 26 p. (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Scena and terzetto: act II scene 1, Holograph sketch in pencil; 6 p.; Uniform title: Act 2 scene 1 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Act II scene 1, Holograph sketch in pencil; 3 p.; Uniform title: Act 2 scene 1 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Scene and terzetto: act II scene 1 and 2, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink, no lyric; 7 p.; Uniform title: Act 2 scene 1 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Terzetto: act II scene 1, Photocopy of holograph sketch; 5 p.; Includes: "She didn't say yes"; Uniform title: Act 2 scene 1 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - Act II scenes I & II: #15, Parts (Box-folder 4/13)
      - Act II scene III, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 40 p.; Includes: "One moment alone" (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Act II scene III: #17, Parts (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Act II scene III, IV and V, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink, annotations in Kern's hand; p. 175-209; Includes: "A new love is old," "One moment alone" (Box-folder 3/3)
      - Act II scene V: street scene, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 19 p. (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Act II scene V: street scene: #20, Parts; Includes: "Victor incidental" "#20b (Try to forget)" (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Al fresco cafe: act I scene 2, Holograph piano score in pencil; [1] p. (incomplete) (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Al fresco cafe: act I scene 2, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano score in ink; 6 p. (Box-folder 3/4)
      - Chandelier: #14, Parts; Note: Based on "I watch the love parade" (Box-folder 5/3)
      - Dance duo: finale act I: act I scene 7, Photocopy of holograph piano-vocal score, no lyric; 3 p. + p. A; Includes: "Don't ask me not to sing" (Box-folder 3/5)
      - Don't ask me not to sing, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 25 p.; Note: dropped from show, used later in Roberta (Box-folder 1/18)
      - Don't ask me not to sing, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 5 p. (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Don't esk [sic], Holograph piano score/sketch in ink; [1] p.; Note: this sketch material later used in Music in the Air (Box-folder 3/6)
      - Duettino: act I scene 4, Ms. piano-vocal score/sketch in pencil, no lyric; 6 p. (Box-folder 3/7)
      - Entr'acte, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink and pencil; 30 p. (Box-folder 1/19)
      - Entr'acte, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink, some lyric and stage directions in Kern's hand; p. 147-174; Includes: "Act II scene I" "I watch the love parade" "The night was made for love" "She didn't say yes"; Note: Included is an earlier version of "She didn't say yes" using a theme from "Act I scene I" (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Entr'acte: #12, Parts (Box-folder 5/4)
      - Finale act I, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 38 p. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Finale act I, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink and pencil; 10 p. (incomplete) (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Finale act I, Ms. choral parts and piano score in pencil, no lyric; [3] p. (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Finale act I: #11, Parts (Box-folder 5/5)
      - Finale ultimo, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 17 p.; Includes: "I watch the love parade" (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Finale ultimo: #22, Parts (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Finaletto act I scene III, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 21 p. (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Finaletto act I scene III, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink; 12 p. (p. 1 is a pasteover); Note on original t.p. in Kern's hand; Photocopy of holograph 2-piano score; 13 p. (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Finaletto act I scene III: #6, Parts (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Hh! cha cha! see: If you're for me
      - I watch the love parade: act I scene 4 See also: Act I scene IV, Chandelier See also: Finale ultimo, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink; 12 p. (Box-folder 3/11)
      - I watch the love parade: act I scene 4 See also: Act I scene IV, Chandelier See also: Finale ultimo, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink; 6 p. (Box-folder 3/11)
      - I watch the love parade: act I scene 4 See also: Act I scene IV, Chandelier See also: Finale ultimo, 1st proof for printed piano-vocal score, annotated; p. 3-7 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - I watch the love parade: act I scene 4 See also: Act I scene IV, Chandelier See also: Finale ultimo, Proof for printed piano-vocal score, annotated; p. 3-6 (p. 7 missing) (Box-folder 3/11)
      - If you're for me, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 17 p.; Note: uses the same music as "Hh! cha cha!" (Box-folder 2/4)
      - If you're for me: #21, Parts (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Lied von Eric: act I scene 3, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil, no lyric; 3 p.; Includes: "The breeze kissed your hair" (Box-folder 3/12)
      - Marziale, Holograph sketch in pencil; [1] p.; Note: this is an excerpt from "Poor Pierrot" (Box-folder 3/13)
      - Misunderstood, Ms. piano sketch in pencil; [1] p. (Box-folder 3/14)
      - New death for Pierrot, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 2 p. (Box-folder 2/5)
      - A new love is old see: Act II scene III, IV and V see: She brings you a new smile
      - New terzetto: act II scenes 1 & 2, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink, partial lyric; 8 p.; Includes: "The night was made for love" (Box-folder 3/15)
      - The night was made for love, Copyist's ms. piano-vocal score in ink, some pencil annotations in Kern's hand; 3 p. (Box-folder 3/16)
      - The night was made for love, 1st proof for printed piano-vocal score, annotated; p. 3-5 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - One moment alone See also: Victor's song See also: Act II scene III, IV and V, Ms. (Albert Sirmay) piano-vocal score in pencil, annotations in Kern's hand; 6 p. (Box-folder 3/17)
      - One moment alone See also: Victor's song See also: Act II scene III, IV and V, 1st proof for printed piano-vocal score, annotated; p. 2-5; On t.p.: "This introduction is not in the mood of the song" [it was changed] (Box-folder 3/17)
      - Opening act I scene III, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 22 p.; Includes: "One moment alone" (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Opening act I scene III: #4, Parts (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Opening act I scene 5, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 6 p. (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Opening act I scene 5: #7, Parts (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Opening scene, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 119 p. + 2 p. crossed out (48, 55) (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Opening scene: #1, Parts (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Opening scene: act I scene 1, Holograph piano-vocal score/sketch in pencil; 17 p. (p. 9-10 missing; p. 6 copyist's ms. in ink); Includes: "New picture number" "She didn't say yes" "The night was made for love" (Box-folder 3/18)
      - New material opening act I, Holograph sketch in pencil; 2 p. (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Addendum and change: act I scene 1, Holograph sketch in pencil; 2 p. (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Opening scene: act I scene I, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink and pencil, some lyric in Kern's hand; 22 p. + p. 15a-15c laid in (Box-folder 3/19)
      - New material, opening scene See also: "The passionate pilgrim" (box 3, folder 20), Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink, laid in above, no lyric; 6 p. (Box-folder 3/19)
      - Opening scene VI, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 4 p. (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Opening scene VI: #9, Parts (Box-folder 6/4)
      - Outmarch, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 5 p.; Includes: "Try to forget" "Entr'acte" "If you're for me (Hh! cha! cha!)" (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Outmarch: try to forget: #23, Parts (Box-folder 6/5)
      - The passionate pilgrim, Arranger's holograph (Robert Russell Bennett) full score in ink; 57 p. (Box-folder 2/11)
      - The passionate pilgrim: Act I scene 7 See also: box 3, folder 19, Holograph piano score in pencil; 2 p.; On t.p.: "Insert...p. 14 Act I scene I..." (Box-folder 3/20)
      - The passionate pilgrim: act I scene 7, Ms. (Robert Russell Bennett) piano-vocal score in ink; 19 p.; Includes: "One moment alone" (Box-folder 3/21)